Guide to the Jacob Harvey Family Papers 1811-1994 MS 306
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Harvey Family Papers, 1808-1950; 3.75 Linear feet
  - Subseries II.A. Jacob Harvey Correspondence, 1808-1848; 1.67 Linear feet
    - Jacob Harvey from Robert Emmett, 1829 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
      One letter concerning a mistaken dinner invitation.
    - Jacob Harvey to John Griscom, 1822-1823 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
      Harvey's numerous letters to Griscom were written over the course of a trip to Ireland and England, and discuss such matters as life and society in Ireland, the Irish famine, and various philanthropic efforts. Includes one letter from John Lecky to John Griscom.
    - Jacob Harvey from J. Prescott Hall, 1839 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
      One letter referencing a letter to Lord Lansdowne, written by Harvey, on the topic of the Maine boundary dispute.
    - Jacob Harvey from Francis Hallinan, 1816-1818 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
      Francis Hallinan appears to have been an employee of the Harvey family in Ireland and wrote to Harvey on a number of occasions to report on business affairs.
    - Jacob Harvey from Hosack Family, 1825-1848 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
      One to five letters each from Emily Hosack, Eliza B. Hosack, Nathaniel P. Hosack, and M. Hosack discussing primarily family matters, such as the marriage of Mary Hosack and Jacob Harvey, as well as life and society in New York.
    - Jacob Harvey from John Hughes, 1846-1847 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
      Two letters concerning life and society in Ireland and the United States. Includes a copy of a letter to Reverend Andrew Barden, written by John Hughes, about an inheritance case in which Harvey had involved himself.
    - Jacob Harvey to Andrew Jackson, 1832 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
      One letter discussing the life and accomplishments of Cadwallader D. Colden.
    - Jacob Harvey from Mitchell King, 1842-1847 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
      Numerous letters concerning the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes, with some mention of slavery, and divorce law, in the United States.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Marquess of Lansdowne, 1830-1847 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
      Lord Lansdowne (Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquess of Lansdowne) was at various points in time Chancellor of Exchequer, Home Secretary, and President of the Council of Great Britain, as well as a warm supporter of abolition of the slave trade, and Catholic Emancipation. Correspondence between Lansdowne and Harvey is primarily concerned with the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes, with some discussion of literature and business.
    - Jacob Harvey from William C. Macready, 1833-1835 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
      Three letters.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Lord Morpeth, 1842-1848 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
      Lord Morpeth (George William Frederick Howard, 7th Earl of Carlisle) had a large estate in or near Limerick which seems to have been managed by Jacob Harvey's father. Morpeth also held positions in various English cabinets relative to Irish affairs, and was a vigorous abolitionist. Correspondence between Morpeth and Harvey is ample, and for the most part concerned with politics in the United States, largely the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from General George Pope Morris, 1823-1827 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
      Three letters concerning Harvey's contribution to Morris's publication, the daily New York Evening Mirror. Also includes three letters to Morris from unidentified correspondents.
    - Jacob Harvey from R. A. O'Reilly, 1824-1848 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
      Correspondence between O'Reilly and Harvey is extensive and addresses a variety of subjects. O'Reilly writes frequently from Dublin, but also from London, and generally correspondence is concerned with life, society and politics in Ireland, England, and the United States. Specific attention is paid to trade between the United States and England, and the Irish famine.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Robert Peel, 1846 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
      Two letters exalting the conclusion of the Oregon border dispute.
    - Jacob Harvey from Jonathan Pim, 1847 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
      Several letters concerning Quaker matters and the Irish famine.
    - Jacob Harvey to James K. Polk, 1846 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
      One letter concerning capital punishment relating to the sentencing of a pirate.
    - Jacob Harvey from Tyrone Power, 1840 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
      Two brief letters.
    - Jacob Harvey to the Press, 1831-1847 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
      One letter to the Editor of the "Truth Teller," and one letter to the Editor of the London Times.
    - Jacob Harvey from John Randolph of Roanoke, 1822-1847 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
      Jacob Harvey and John Randolph of Roanoke met on board a ship for England in 1822, after which Harvey became Randolph's agent in New York. Correspondence between Harvey and Randolph is ample and is centered around such topics as the exchange of books, politics, mutual esteem and philosophy. Folder also includes extracts from a number of Randolph's letters as well as a letter to Jacob Harvey from Jonathan Jay Smith on the subject of letters and a publication written by Randolph.
    - Jacob Harvey from M.B. Sampson, 1841-1847 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
      M.B. Sampson was an official of the Bank of England and intensely interested in such fads as homeopathy, vegetarianism, and mesmerism. Correspondence between Sampson and Harvey is ample and concerned with a wide variety of topics, most significantly English and American politics, Harvey's business affairs, and the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Winfield Scott, 1839-1843 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
      One letter expressing gratitute, and one letter on the subject of an unidentified memorandum.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from William H. Seward, 1838-1842 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22)
      Several letters concerned with such topics as education in New York, party politics, slavery, the McLeod Case of 1841, and the Maine boundary dispute.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Marquess of Sligo, 1838-1848 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 23)
      Correspondence between Sligo (Howe Browne, 2nd Marquess of Sligo) and Harvey is extensive and addresses a variety of subjects. Generally the letters are concerned with life, society, and politics in Ireland, England, and the United States. Specific attention is paid to the Irish famine, the Maine boundary dispute, and Loco Focos. Also included are a number of letters written by his Sligo's wife, H. Catherine Sligo, during a period when the Marquess was incapable of writing legibly.
    - Jacob Harvey from James Spedding, 1840-1845 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
      Several letters generally concerned with international politics, most significantly the Irish famine and the Maine and Oregon boundary disputes.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from T. Spring Rice (Baron Monteagle), 1832-1846 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
      Correspondence between Spring Rice and Harvey is ample and primarily concerned with international politics, most specifically those of Ireland, England, and the United States.
    - Jacob Harvey to Lord Stanley, 1836 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
      One letter concerning the Church of Ireland.
    - Jacob Harvey to Jeremiah Thompson, 1820-1827 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
      A series of five letters — of which the second is missing — addressed to the Park Place Club in Nightly Council Assembled. These letters recount Harvey's experience during his Tour of the West, and like his travel journals, comment upon architecture and landscapes, modes of transportation, travel conditions, and accommodations. Harvey's letters are highly anecdotal, and pay particular attention to politics, slavery, Quaker matters, and Irish immigrants. Also included is a single letter to Jeremiah Thompson, which was commenced by Harvey but never sent, that details a serious business mishap.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Martin Van Buren, 1838-1848 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
      Two letters concerning a delicate matter involving a W. M. Price.
    - Jacob Harvey from Jonathan Wainwright, 1835 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
      One letter expressing condolences on the death of an unnamed person (possibly David Hosack).
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Daniel Webster, 1840-1841 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
      Three letters concerning the Maine boundary dispute and the promotion of peace between England and the United States. Reference is made to Lansdowne and Monteagle.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Silas Wright, 1838-1842 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
      At the time of his correspondence with Harvey, Wright served as Chairman of the Finance Committee in the United States Senate. Correspondence between Wright and Harvey is ample, and concerned with party politics, the election of 1840, Martin Van Buren, and the United States Bank and Sub-treasury.
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Correspondents A-H, 1821-1848 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
      Correspondents include: John Agnew (?) (1827); Joseph Arc-- (from Brighton) (1837); William B. Astor (1846); A. M. Church (1833); F. W. Conway (1847); Clarence C. Cook (1843); Miss Edgeworth (1843); John Ford (1839); Jane J Lennell (1848); -- Graves (1846); Robert Greenhow (1828); James Haughton (?) (1846); Francis L. Hawkes (1836); Jack Healy (1821); John H. Hicks (1845).
    - Jacob Harvey to/from Correspondents K-W, 1816-1847 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
      Correspondents include: D. S. Kennedy (undated); Mary Leadbeater (1816-1817); Frank Lloyd (1827-1828); R. B. Minturn (1841); Lady Ann Monck (1847); George Raperlje (1833-1834); David Sears (1847); R. Sherwood (1836); Daniel B Smith (1819); Bishop Spencer (1842); James S. Stopford (1828); George Wilkes (1839).
    - Jacob Harvey from Unidentified Correspondent, 1838 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
      One lengthy letter, written from Hastings, concerning what appears to be business affairs.
    - Jacob Harvey to Unidentified Correspondents, 1840s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12)
      Three letters addressed to a Lord (possibly Morpeth and/or Lansdowne) on the subject of the Oregon boundary dispute.
    - Jacob Harvey from Unidentified Correspondent, 1847 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13)
      One circular on the subject of the Irish Famine.
    - Jacob Harvey (?) from George Dawson-Damer, Sir Joseph Laffan, William Watson, 1835-1841 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 14)
      Three letters which are not explicitly addressed to Harvey.
    - Irish Letters, 1816-1829 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 15)
      These letters had been labeled "Curious Letter...", "Curious Irish Letter", or "Irish Letter". For the most part, they detail the various misfortunes of their authors, or beg favors of their recipients.
    - Copy of J.M. Harvey's Will, 1833 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 16)
    - Extract from Dr. David Hosack's Memoranda, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 17)
    - Member List for Friday Evening Club, 1847 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 18)
    - Poetry, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 19)
      Authors include: Jacob Harvey; Warren Hastings, copied by Randolph; Mr. Biddle; Cowper.
    - Lunch Poetry, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 20)
      Auhors include: J.S. Hone; Halleck; A Bleecker.
    - Irish Songs, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous Literary Efforts, 1838, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous Literary Efforts, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 23)
      Includes a "Fairy Tale by M Harvey (Mary Harvey?), written when ten years old".
    - Newspaper Clippings (1 of 3), 1820s-1840s, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 24)
      Subjects include: The Creole Case (1842, undated); Irish Affairs (1847, undated) (clipping "Supplement to The Dublin Evening Post, 1816" moved to oversized); Maine & Oregon border disputes, State Debts (1842-1846, undated); Miscellaneous (1822-1823, undated).
    - Newspaper Clippings (2 of 3), 1830s-1840s, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 25)
      Subjects include: Irish Stories (1831-1832); Letters on Catholicisim by Jacob Harvey & Brownlow correspondence on Catholicism (1840-1842); Articles by Jacob Harvey on remittances of money by Irish in America (1844-1847).
    - Newspaper Clippings. Oversize. (3 of 3), 1846-1847 (Box OS-Small, Folder --)
    - Portrait Engravings from Magazines, 1830s, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous Envelopes, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 27)
      Original evelopes that could not be matched with any letters, and a portion of an envelope that was used by Feinses to identify correspondence to and from notable persons.
  - Subseries II.B. Jacob Harvey Journals, 1816-1823; 0.83 Linear feet
    This subseries contains notes, journals, and a commonplace book written by Jacob Harvey between the years 1816 and 1823. Significant themes which emerge throughout the subseries are Harvey's Quaker background; his continued attachment to Ireland and his growing concern for the plight of his people, both in Ireland and as immigrants in the United States; and his fervent objection to slavery in general, and especially in the U.S. The container list further identifies subjects at the folder level.
    Journals have been organized chrononlogically, according to the date of the first entry. In the case where there are multiple copies of a single journal, what appears to be the original is filed ahead of what appears to be the copy, or final draft.
    - Trip from Belfast to New York, 1816 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
      This journal provides an account of Jacob Harvey's journey from Belfast to New York, in the company of Abraham and Mary Bell, as well as his initial impression of the United States during his first few months in New York. Harvey meticulously notes travel conditions as well as the habits and attitudes of his companions and, upon his arrival in New York, the immigration regulations imposed upon himself and his fellow passengers.
      The second half of the journal records the landscape, population, and architecture of New York and its environs, including such towns as Jamaica, Flushing, Brooklyn, and Elizabethtown in New Jersey. Harvey pays special attention to military structures and monuments, such as one erected on the site of the Burr-Hamilton Duel. He also remarks upon Independence Day celebrations in New York, and the continuous arrival of Irish immigrants to the city.
    - Trip to Philadelphia (1 of 2), 1817 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
      This journal provides an account of Jacob Harvey's trip from New York to Philadelphia and its environs, along with a last minute excursion to Baltimore. As in his other travel journals, Harvey diligently records the architectural landscape and the attitudes of the people in the cities he encounters, as well as modes of transportation and travel conditions. Entries in this journal are particularly concerned with the manner by which people sustain themselves, be it industry, trade, or agriculture, and he often records market values for a variety of goods. Harvey also remarks upon significant institutions, such as the Museum of Baltimore and the Franklin Library in Philadelphia, state prisons and hospitals, abolition societies, and European schools for Native Americans.
    - Trip to Philadelphia (2 of 2), 1817 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
      This journal appears to be a copy — or final draft — of the journal described above. It appears to have undergone a significant amount of revision, although the content of the two journals is closely aligned.
    - Commonplace Book, 1819-1820 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
      Jacob Harvey's Commonplace Book more closely resembles a journal. The initial entries are centered around excerpts from published works, most notably an 1817 Haitian Publication, titled Réflexions politiques sur quelques ouvrages et journaux francais concernant Hayti, which is concerned with the 1791-1804 Haitian Revolution. Harvey also records notable cultural events, such as Charles Guille's jump from a hot air balloon in New York on 2 August 1819 and the Annual Culmination of the students of Columbia College. Other entries are concerned with government, on both a global and a local scale, and record such events as the Adams-Onis Treaty as well as the proceedings and scandal surrounding a few notable court-cases. The final entries, being compiled from Harvey's travel notes, most closely resemble his other journals.
    - Notes on Trip to Washington, Mt. Vernon, and Baltimore, 1820 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
      This account comprises a few loose pages of notes which record a trip from Washington D.C., where Harvey pays a visit to George Washington's Estate at Mt.Vernon, to Baltimore. He pays special attention to topics of race and the conditions of slavery in these areas. Also included is a separate sheet of notes which record proceedings at the House of Representatives during a vote. Harvey later compiles these notes, in narrative form, in his Commonplace Book.
    - Account of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia/Account of the Yearly Meeting in New York (1 of 2), 1820 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
      There is a typescript associated with this journal that appears to have been copied from the Account of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia/Account of the Yearly Meeting in New York (2 of 2), which is assumed to be a copy — or final draft — of the journal described here. The typescript is an excerpt only, and does not represent this account in its entirety.
      This journal provides an account of Quaker Yearly Meetings in Philadelphia and New York. Harvey records the daily operations of the meetings themselves, along with his observations of member conduct, and occasionally his personal opinion regarding the topics discussed.
      In his account of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia, Harvey records nearly 2,000 members, in attendance from Baltimore, New York, and London, as well as from Rhode Island, Ohio, Indiana, Virginia, and North Carolina. The meeting addresses such topics as the rights of Native Americans and the descendants of Africans, with special attention to donations that were to be made in support of these groups. Other topics include Quaker affairs, such as member anxiety regarding the blending of Societies, Quaker presence in the press and the perceived public opinion of the Society, and how members ought to behave during meetings and in daily life.
      Harvey's account of the Yearly Meeting in New York records many of the same topics, but reveals a more morally stringent attitude specific to the New York Society. Harvey records a number of discussions regarding member conduct, especially on the topic of member association with non-Quakers. Elias Hicks emerges as a figure vehemently against the cultivation of relationships outside the immediate community, and here Harvey asserts his personal opinion in opposition to Hicks, as well as that on a number of other topics.
    - Account of the Yearly Meeting in Philadelphia/Account of the Yearly Meeting in New York (2 of 2), 1820 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
      There is a typescript associated with this journal. This journal appears to be a copy — or final draft — of the journal described above.
    - Tour to the Falls of Niagara and Canada (1 of 2), 1820 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
      There is a typescript associated with this journal that appears to have been copied from the Tour to the Falls of Niagara and Canada (2 of 2), which is assumed to be a copy — or final draft — of the journal described here.
      This journal provides an account of Jacob Harvey's trip from New York to Canada and back, along with his experience at the burgeoning tourist destination of Niagara Falls. As in his other travel journals, Harvey diligently records the landscape and monuments he encounters, as well as modes of transportation and travel conditions. Harvey often indicates the type of goods cultivated by various regions and communities, in addition to the religion(s) practiced.
    - Tour to the Falls of Niagara and Canada (2 of 2), 1820 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
    - Tour of the West (1 of 2), 1820 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
      This journal provides an account of Jacob Harvey's trip from New York westward and back, through Maryland, Pennsylvania, what is now West Virginia, Ohio, Kentucky and Indiana. As in his other travel journals, Harvey meticulously records the landscape, architecture, and attitudes of the people in the communities that he encounters, as well as modes of transportation and travel conditions. Entries in this journal are particularly concerned with the government of each state, and with slavery. In Frankfort, Kentucky, Harvey records his visit to the House of Representatives and the Senate, and in Corydon, Indiana he remarks upon the general attitude of the community toward the Monroe/Tompkins Presidential Candidacy. The town of Troy, Indiana is the farthest point west reached by Harvey, and the reason for the trip appears to have been business to be conducted in this town.
    - Tour of the West (2 of 2), 1820 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    - Voyage Round Long Island, 1821 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
      There is a typescript associated with this journal. See Typescript. Journal, Voyage Round Long Island, 1821.
      Much of this account records the habits and attitudes of Harvey's travel companions as well as the state of his accommodations on board the steamboat. Some small attention is given to the natural landscape and the communities he encounters.
    - Notebooks, 1822-1823 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6-7)
      Includes six notebooks comprising an account of Jacob Harvey's trip from America to Ireland, where he spent nearly a year visiting with family and friends. Many entries record Quaker meetings as well as discussions about Slavery in the United States. The notebooks also reference several family names present in his correspondence, including the Braithwaites, the Bells, T. Spring Rice, and Lord Lansdowne, among many others. Reference is also made to the African Institution in London, to which Harvey was introduced by his friend and sometimes travel companion John Randolph of Roanoke.
  - Subseries II.C. Mary Hosack Harvey Correspondence and Scrapbook, 1810-1950; 0.53 Linear feet
    This subseries comprises Mary Hosack Harvey's correspondence between the years 1812 and 1871, including letters of condolence upon the death of Jacob Harvey, in addition to poetry written for her, and newspaper clippings and a scrapbook kept by her.
    Mary Hosack Harvey's correspondence is generally concerned with life and society in New York and in Ireland. Letters from her family comprise the most significant portion of her correspondence, the bulk of which were written after the death of her husband in 1848. She received letters from her siblings Alexander, Emily, and Nathaniel Hosack, her daughters Mary and Rebecca Harvey, and her niece Emily Rodgers. She also received letters from her relatives Hannah Harvey Todhunter and Mary C. Harvey in Ireland. Of particular interest are nine folders of letters from her brother-in-law in Ireland, William Henry Harvey, who was a prominent botanist of the era. These letters span nearly twenty years and chronicle significant family events such as marriages, illnesses, and deaths, as well as parts of W.H. Harvey's career. The container list further identifies subjects at the folder level.
    Overall, the subseries is arranged by correspondent, with documents other than correspondence situated at the end of the subseries. Correspondence is further arranged as follows: